this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-radio.net
sc radio is brought to you by the ieee
computer society by ieee software
magazine
online at computer.org software
for software engineering radio this is
robert blumen
today i have with me sean knapp
sean is the founder and ceo of ascend io
prior to ascend he was a co-founder cto
and chief product officer at uyawa and
before that
an engineer at google sean has degrees
in computer science from stanford
university
sean welcome to software engineering
radio
thanks for having me robert we are going
to be talking today about data pipeline
automation let's start out with what is
a data pipeline
yeah i think you know the data pipeline
has
uh morphed over the course of of time uh
traditionally people have really thought
about data pipelines
in the notion of an etl context where
we're extracting data from one location
moving it around potentially
transforming it and dropping it into
another
that could be pulling data whether it's
from
a sensor in an iot landscape or out of a
spreadsheet or moving a file from
one file system to another and
oftentimes the data pipelines are moving
data into
a data warehouse or into a bi
application
over the course of the last five ten
years
data pipelines have become even more
important because they've not just been
moving
records but they've been moving large
volumes of data and information and
they've been doing more
complex things to that data so
everything from
really advanced analytics to machine
learning
and uh tackling far more interesting
complex use cases
as industries have matured and evolved
you're talking about large volumes
how big it's interesting that you know
we for example work with
uh folks who do everything from they're
moving around
thousands of records per day or you know
just kilobytes of information
to people who are pushing around
billions and actually the largest says
uh even over a trillion records per day
where they're moving around
and so data pipelines are really
designed
hopefully are designed well to cater to
pretty much
any scale if you went into a business
maybe you could give an order of
magnitude how many pipelines does a
typical business
have yeah so the we see
smaller businesses and smaller teams may
only have
a dozen or a few dozen data pipelines
oftentimes it's a data pipeline it
corresponds to how many data sources
you have whether it's entities coming
out of your transactional databases or
how you're collecting uh data from users
inside of your applications
and so that's usually one of the things
that dictates how many data pipelines
you have
the second thing and this is what using
can create a pretty large explosion of
the number of data pipelines
is frankly how many data products
derived
data sets you're creating on top of
those
and oftentimes that can lead to hundreds
of data pi bonds
we're going to be talking about a bit
more rigorous way
to think about data pipelines but i'm
wondering if this is like
another area we've addressed which is
business process automation where
every business has business processes
they
just didn't know it like the famous
character in literature who didn't
realize he was speaking prose
[Laughter]
yes it's uh it is true you know i'd say
on a weekly basis uh we talk with a lot
of different companies out there
and you'll see oftentimes they're even
talking about
oh well you know we don't do data
pipelines we
collect all of our data in our data lake
and or our data warehouse
and we use eot the
extract load transform where you're
processing data as you query it out of a
data location like a lake or a warehouse
and as we dive in deeper they end up
actually having
huge numbers of very ad hoc like
informal
data pipelines that are moving data into
that lake or into that warehouse or
taking all that raw data and compressing
it down and refining it and enriching it
so that their
actual eot style queries are faster and
more efficient
and so as you start to peel back the few
layers they really
very quickly realize they have pipelines
all over the place
just didn't realize and weren't thinking
of them as data pipelines themselves
so yes totally wholeheartedly agree so
what are the
typical building blocks in pipelines
yeah so when we think about the building
blocks inside of a typical pipeline
there's
a couple of ways of thinking about it
one is obviously
the raw technologies
and capabilities you need those usually
boil down to
somewhere to store the data which is can
be a lake it can be a warehouse
you need tools to process the data
oftentimes that's uh spark or kafka
or the warehouse itself to process the
data
and then the third ingredient building
block you usually
need is some sort of orchestration tool
the thing that's keeping tabs on
what processing should run on what piece
of data when and why
so those are sort of the three
categories of
sort of raw components then what we
when we think about more logically what
we're doing with a data pipeline
it usually conforms to the data
lifecycle itself
so first how do i ingest the data
collect it from a bunch of different
locations
get it into at least a standard storage
format oftentimes
snappy compressed parquet files uh if
it's in your lake
and then once you get your data ingested
you start to go through the stages of
cleaning that data normalizing it
and then you you'll start to go through
the stages of enriching it joining uh
different data sets so you can get
richer records that uh then usually roll
into
and start to fork out from there into
advanced analytics machine learning
pipelines
uh and that's where you really get to
start to do a lot of the really
interesting work on the data
and strip to generate these derived
insights and derived data products
so those are usually the three or four
stages generating data sets
that you are going to use as training
data
for machine learning models or if
they're already trained
you may be running the models against
that data yeah a little bit of both
uh on the on the ml side we spend more
time with folks who are generating a lot
of these
curated high fidelity data sets to train
the models
on is usually where at least at ascend
most of our customers
use us for and then on the
analytic side is you know for example if
you're collecting
uh two billion data points a day of
users who are using your app
all right you can't do ad hoc queries
very cost effectively and efficiently
against two billion data points every
single day for your bi report
and so creating these you know whether
you call them data cubes or just
sort of compressed roll-ups of data so
that you can then query them very
quickly
off of not two billion raw records per
day but
can be compressed down to a data set
that's in the millions or less
that's what we see a lot of people using
those downstream data pipelines for
so are we largely talking about
things that are let me call it isolated
pipelines or data comes in from some
original source let's say it's
price quotes or temperature sensor goes
through some pipeline
reaches the end point where people can
do analysis on it
or are we also talking about data that
is already
in the enterprise like you have an oltp
database from
your website and now you need to get
that data somewhere else so people can
do something
else with it and maybe even you'd start
chaining pipelines together
totally that's a really a great point
which is
pipelines are like these really flexible
lego building blocks where all of them
are different sizes and shapes often
times
but you compose them together
and what we see is this huge movement
right now
to not just have a big data pipeline
that's like you know the beacons from
your users that are using your
application
but we see a huge amount of interest in
i want to grab all my data out of my
oltp database i need a cdc pipeline
that's getting that into my unified data
store so i can actually do
aggregate analysis on top of all of the
data that my
company has okay so every business
then is pulling data out of a ltp
database and putting it in a
data warehouse so whether they call out
a pipeline or not they have a pipeline
it's very true okay and let's pick that
as a canonical example you just
run a big query that selects out of one
database
and inserts into another or is there
something in between that's doing
something to the data
yeah it's a good question hopefully
there's something in between
that's helping to optimize that a little
bit for example
a really simple approach is
if you're trying to replicate the data
you have in your ootp
database inside of let's say your data
warehouse or your data lake
there's usually a couple of different
approaches a cdc
pipeline that isn't actually querying
the database but going off of the
the cdc or the replication logs
of the database itself is a really
common paradigm
because you're not beating up on your
core otp database
if you don't have that a lot of other
folks usually will then try and uh
directly query that database using
things like last modified time
to just get the the changes in the data
because you're trying to
at least the biggest fear is always
running on a big data system you can
very easily crush your otp database
and so you're trying to as efficiently
as possible take the data out of there
and get it into a system that is much
bigger and much
much stronger and what we'll find is
oftentimes a good practice is to at
least at the first stage of that
pipeline to not
perform any radical transformations on
that data it's safer to actually keep a
copy
of that data in cheap storage put it in
s3 gcs azure blob store something where
you're paying a center to a gig
and you can keep a copy of that because
you can always go back to it if you need
to
and then this this is what's really cool
about data pipelines
and etl is it's never really one
transformation it's not really etl
it's usually something that's closer to
a regular expression of like
etl plus where you're constantly you
know etl tltl
and you're making cascading transforms
and dropping off those derived data sets
were appropriate
you dropped the acronym in there cdc
would you
define that for listeners please sure
cdc has changed data capture
one of the things that is really
interesting about sort of database which
is designed
for high levels of mutability and
updates to individual records is
trying to capture all of those changes
over time and get those
into your data lake or your data
warehouse
is really valuable so you can just get
those deltas
and apply them to the other copy of data
you have elsewhere
are we generally talking about things
that live in the batch mode
where you're doing a chunk of data runs
in a batch window maybe
the next day or an hour later you do
another chunk or the streaming
world where every little bit or
every minute of data is trickling
through the pipeline into the endpoint
yeah what we're seeing uh is
a hybridization of batch and streaming
uh you know when we look at how a lot of
the industries
evolved over the course of time we all
started with batch
and it was like a nightly cron you
started at at 1am to make sure all of
your log files showed up in your
hdfs cluster and then you started
crunching up a ton of data
and the pendulum swung for a while
really strongly towards streaming and
trying to push everything through
streaming uh very very quickly
but the reality is you actually want
both and you need a hybridization of
those two
some form of batch processing allows you
to do more complex analysis
because you can correlate data that
would not naturally be within the same
time window
and some form of streaming allows you to
do really rapid propagation
for analysis that needs to happen very
quickly
and so this notion of hybridizing batch
and streaming has actually started to
get rolled up
into the the concept of data flows where
we rather than say i want to run this
pipeline every
10 minutes or 10 hours or pick your
interval
and on streaming which is it's just
continuously running but i have a tight
window of data
the notion behind a data flow is not
overly new but it's more of a
descriptive model that says here's the
correlation of data here's
how i want to process it and you try and
move data through
as quickly and efficiently as you can
based on the calculations itself
and so for example how we've implemented
inside of ascend
is using high frequency micro batch we
grab small chunks of data and move them
through as efficiently as we can
based off the availability of the data
itself
use the word data flow i have not run
across this
is this uh well understood or agreed
upon
uh abstraction in this field uh
it's as a generic term yes not in the
big data notion yet
um when we talk about data flows uh
and the concept's been around for a
while google when they actually
first created beam apache beam
had branded it as dataflow and actually
pulled that back
and open sourced it as apache beam and
kept their branded uh
in google cloud notion of data flow and
the reason being that
one obviously they needed to separate
their the branding but as they described
the notion of a data flow beam does a
better job of hybridizing this notion of
batch and streaming
and focuses more on the data itself as
opposed to the time synchronization
you're trying
to apply to it when i asked you about
building blocks you
mentioned the orchestration layer as one
of the building blocks
i'm pretty sure that a lot of
organizations are not using
orchestration layers and when we have
talked
to other guests about workflow process
automation that is also the case
there that implementations are
especially if you don't conceive of what
you're doing as an
instance of a much more general class of
problems that has a general solution
if you go into organizations that are
not using an orchestration
layer how are these pipelines
implemented
yeah it's a really good question i i'd
say
in general solving of the orchestration
problem
which is i would contend the most
critical problem
today for data engineering i think is
very much in its infancy today and
it's very much to be expected right the
last five year ten years has been about
how do i store more data process more
data or move it around faster
and we've been basically using bubble
gum and baling wire to
glue together these pipelines and it to
me
the industry looks very similar to
what container orchestration and look
like probably
four or five years ago sort of the
pre-kubernetes era
right where we hadn't moved too heavily
the declarative base models with
a well standardized understanding of
what are the components in the building
blocks
and we see this a lot like it across
different domains and so
what we see right now when companies
don't have really advanced orchestration
tools
they're using uh generic workflow
engines like jenkins
to just run you know it's sort of think
of it as like
crawling with maybe a small dag a
directed acyclic graph
where they're running a few scripts
there's uh other open source tools like
airflow or uzi or luigi these are all
tools that
help you create these dags to execute
but they're still very uh it's still
just very early
because they're running code uh but they
don't have context
and so you know if we look at all the
benefits we've seen
with the introduction of kubernetes for
running our infrastructure
uh and how much can be offloaded by the
core capabilities of case
we've yet to see this really happen in
data pipeline orchestration
if you took a step back even from
organizations that are using
jenkins you'd find a combination of a
lot of
crime jobs and manual steps yeah is that
fair
yep it's a a cron job with a bit of bash
or probably a lot of bash in python
that's then launching clusters and
starting jobs and
shipping off either sql queries to a
warehouse or
more often than not spark jobs to a
spark cluster
does an organization have some kind of
either time constraints or other
slos in relation to these pipelines
pretty much every data pipeline has some
slo
which is always a really brittle thing
to accomplish because
the notion behind the slo usually when
you have
what is a very manual orchestration
approach right you have
acron job or some basic orchestration
thing that says run this job with this
many resources
this many nodes and this much cpu memory
etc
at this time your data is never static
right the
nature of your data changes
significantly the volumes increase they
decrease and so
all of a sudden whatever those
configuration settings
you know you had that you checked into
your repo and your cron jobs running on
your slo is always at risk because the
parameters of the data itself will
change
and the configurations you sent did it
and so that's
one of the most brutal aspects of
traditional data pipelines is
the slo itself you mentioned
dag's direct ac graph i want to come
back to that when we talk about modeling
but
staying on the reliability issue for a
bit longer what are some of the things
that can go wrong
in a pipeline a lot so
pipelines tend to be far more brittle in
nature
for a handful of reasons part of it is
we have no data pipeline engine
we have a processing engine like spark
but we oftentimes don't have
the pipeline engine above it that
provides that resilience
and so you you end up with a few things
part of it is at an infrastructure
level you lose nodes you lose jobs
uh we run for example all of our data
processing on spot
and preemptable instances to keep costs
really low for
both ourselves and our customers but
those nodes can come in they can go out
no nodes are fully isolated you're
running other spark jobs on those nodes
at the same time so you can
end up with resource conflicts and so
between node failures pod failures
potential
booming because too much coalesced on a
single node
or single pod you tend to see a lot of
infrastructure failures that are very
recoverable but you need the
intelligence layer on top to know that
they're recoverable
the other thing you'll oftentimes see
is there's uh bad data
like all of a sudden a corrupted record
comes through
right and having a system that knows
what are the semantics of that
is it okay to ignore that corrupted
record or do you actually have to halt
the pipeline and alert on it
it's the second category it more of a
data integrity
itself and those are two of the most
common breaks we see
if you have jobs people are depending on
them to run or other jobs are depending
perhaps you have a pipeline that gets
data
into your analytics database and maybe
you have analytics jobs and people need
that data
do you have a risk of cascading failures
oh my gosh yes yeah totally the
cascading failure off of like a broken
pipeline that has
18 stages and it gets fubared at
stage three and all of a sudden
everything else behind it's now
blocked this is like the classic data
engineering all the way out to
uh data analyst and the executive report
that gets emailed out every morning
at 7 00 am that didn't go out that's
always the scary stuff and it's the
prototypical example of breaks that can
be caught early
and recovered from and so on that that
creates a lot of friction inside of most
companies
how do people recover when they have
this cascading failure
someone have to go and restart a bunch
of jobs or run them by hand
usually yes for most uh i'd say most
folks
really end up having to go kickstart
the pipeline it usually ends up being
somebody gets paged at
six a.m because they noticed that it
didn't work
you kick-start the job again you give it
twice as many resources
and more memory because it owned before
or something along those lines
you just jump start the the pipeline
again and try and let it catch up
this is one of those ones where you know
we worked really hard this is
sort of one of the core beliefs behind
why i
even started ascend was there is a
system there is
technically possible to create a system
that can be smart enough to say
oh i know all of the downstream systems
everything
and how long it takes and how long it's
all historically taken
and i can profile the data and see the
profile of the data that's coming in has
actually fundamentally changed
i'd say while the standard affair of
like
hey whatever parameters i had before
just no longer worked and the thing
borked uh and i have to kickstart it
that definitely
shouldn't be the future things like
fully dynamic parameterization based off
of profiling of the data itself
automated recovery with some level of of
healthy growth and parameters like all
these things are very technically
solvable problems you're talking about
if i understand this last point
job might have failed because either the
business has grown or on that particular
day there was more data and it was sized
at a certain size and just ran out of
resources
so it's not as simple as start the job
run it again but someone has to look and
say okay we need to increase the size of
this cluster and then try to run it
again
and hopefully it'll finish is that more
or less yeah exactly it could be hey
it was black friday and we actually just
had more people come to our online store
than we thought
like i i watch a bunch of the data
pipelines we have through
our internal systems and for example
we just do dynamic parameterization of
the resources and
so you actually can see that it's
completely flexes
based off of the profile of the data the
complexity of the sql
or pi spark or scala transforms you're
doing
and so it's very possible to flex these
resources
if your orchestration system understands
the what's happening to the data itself
and i think that's the
this next era of orchestration is really
around
how do we actually have code and data
aware
orchestration sean we've been talking
about what these pipelines are
what can go wrong in the semi-manual
world
we are going to talk now more about
automation but
preceding that let's talk a bit about
how you model
the pipelines because in order to
automate you do need
a bit more rigorous modeling and that's
where these
directed acyclic graphs dags come in
that you referred to earlier expand more
on what the dag
is and and why is that a useful way
to model a data pipeline yeah a great
question so
dags the dags these directed asycate
graphs are a way of describing
dependencies
and an order of operations traditional
dags
have really focused on code they
essentially say this
code this job needs to run before the
and successfully complete before this
other job runs
and oftentimes it's not just entirely
serial but they can
fan out and say this job needs to run
then these three can run in parallel
before
two of them can run and converge back on
one job
but it's a way of describing
dependencies
of blocks of code and
that's why they become uh helpful in
creating data pipelines
is oftentimes you're creating one data
set
that then flows into another data set
and you need this these dags to specify
the dependency of those they can also
and this is something that we've done at
ascend which is to
restructure it from code centric to data
centric
where if you can change that model for
example if you think about this in a sql
context
you can actually create sql queries that
generate incremental data sets and then
the the center of gravity is actually on
that data itself and say
this data is a query on top of this data
which is a query on top of these sets of
data
and same thing applies around dags just
a data centric approach as opposed to a
code
centric approach i'm not sure i
understood that last point
in some of the reading i was doing about
this it if i understood there's
controversy about is the dag of all the
steps you do
like step one pull the data out of
this one database step two change all
the date formats
step three loaded into the destination
database
so we'd have a very simple dag with
three
no three nodes and two edges of steps or
is the dag about what happens to
each element of data and now
is my question addressing this last
point that you made
that i didn't fully understand your your
question highlights
what's sort of a traditional dag
describing the code that says perform
each one of these incremental steps
it's more of an imperative construct
we're just simply describing the
take data from one state to the next
state uh and that's really a classic
dag of it's a code centric tag uh
perform these steps
the sort of new wave
is really around declarative uh data
pipelines
and to be declarative you actually focus
less on the steps of like extract from
here
do this transform checked states and so
on and instead
you focus just on i have data over here
i want to transform it with this sql
query that declares the next
drive data set and
how data is extracted out transformed
moved where and which
pieces of data like what time you run it
at
what data's already been processed
versus what hasn't all of that goes away
and is the responsibility of the
orchestration system
in a declarative model with dags we did
another show
on terraform really focusing on the
declarative model
which is useful for the programmer
because it may be
easier to specify and then there's some
kind of
compilation that generates
the steps that the underlying system has
to take but it may be
easier for the programmer or maybe you
have such a thing as a data pipeline
analyst not to think about it that way
is that what's going on here as well
yeah very much so i i think we're seeing
this move
both in in terraform for infrastructure
management for kubernetes and container
orchestration
and now in data pipelines the the
declarative approach of just
describe the expected end state of your
world and
have a domain specific context aware
engine that sits underneath it that can
figure out how to take you to that
expected end state
but i'm obviously very biased towards uh
terraform and kate says
we use them both extensively inside of
this end
and so we've been adhering to these
models for a really long time
if the world goes in this direction or
maybe it already has then
is there a job description of the data
pipeline analyst 2
is focusing on coding up these
declarative
pipelines yeah i i do think so
um you know we've uh talked about
i actually wrote an article about this
earlier on in the year about the notion
of the citizen data engineer
and we've talked about the citizen data
scientists for a long time of people who
come in from
adjacent domains and we see a lot of
increased demand for data engineers and
historically data engineering came up
through
distributed systems and you had both
like a math and a stats and a
distributed systems background
but the focus was more around moving
data around and managing of the
underlying systems
and what we see is this notion rapidly
expanding
around data engineering which is
actually now the fastest growing
job for software engineering and tech
job which is
the idea being you no longer have to
worry about
like how many nodes are you running like
have you tweaked into the jvm
and actually don't even have to worry
about things like partition persistence
and data invalidation and lineage
tracking and data integrity
instead it is like this data pipeline
analyst as you described that can
up level to focus on the data itself
as opposed to the internal and
underlying operations
just as we've seen software engineers be
more and more empowered building on top
of kubernetes
we get the same thing for uh entirely
new
people able to now build on top of this
notion of declarative
pipelines uh data pipelines so now we've
covered
for a bit how you represent the pipeline
i want to move more into automation
this question you probably already
answered it or
listeners could figure out what your
response would be from things you've
already said
you go into uh organization and they
have a bunch of cron scripts that run
and bash scripts what is a case for
automation sleep is usually a good one
obviously the listeners uh can't see my
shirt but i'm actually
wearing something that we we took at aws
free invent which is
the pipelines uh served to neat and it
was about this pipeline sucks speak easy
where the joke was
there seems to be this very strong
correlation between people who wanted
the free whiskey and people who had to
deal with data pipelines all day and
the the sort of general notion is look
like maintaining
uh data pipelines is really hard they
break all the time we're always tweaking
we're always tuning
and the the biggest case for
really advanced automation is no
different than we saw
with terraform and kubernetes is it
makes life easier you spend far less of
your time
like plumbing up things and far more of
your time actually architecting and
designing and building
so for engineers software engineers who
are creating data pipelines for data
engineers or
are doing the same it frees you to
spend less time maintaining and more
time building is there a name
for the broad class of tools which
solves this problem
not yet to be really frank the
there's i'd say a lot of debate
currently
what tools fit inside of the broader
data engineering
suite itself and that ecosystem we have
things for data processing
we have data orchestration but this is a
very generic
notion today then we also still have
a lot tied to the the new
ideas around data ops which is boring
obviously for devops but
same sort of core principles of how do
we enable more people to build faster
safely just apply to
data as opposed to software and so
there's
a handful of different categories that i
would already sub categories
that fit here but i think ultimately it
really boils down to
this is at the core it's data
engineering it's a different
kind of engineering that very much
needs full-fledged product uh and
full-fledged technology
to really help people build faster so
this question i'm going to ask you
what is the high-level architecture of a
pipeline automation engine you could
either talk about your product or if
all the offerings in this space have
roughly the same components what does
the generic
product look like yeah there's a great
question
the generic product really at the core
is a scheduler
the i'd say the most common thing we see
pretty much
uniformly is it's a scheduler that runs
some form of jobs with some notion of a
dag
it will usually maintain some level of
state
and this is i think really where the
biggest difference in
different technologies comes out is it
really comes down to
how much state do you maintain and if
you look at it as a bit of a spectrum
you know cron
at one end of the extreme maintains
practically no state
a handful of tools will maintain a bit
of state
things like uh they know they ran some
job at some period of time they don't
know
what the job did or what it produced but
they know that they ran a job
and that it may be triggered another job
so it's very job-centric we're starting
to see
things get a little bit better more
generically across the industry around
some level of maintaining that there's a
notion of data
for example that hey i have a catalog i
can register data with
but i really believe that the most
extreme and really where we've invested
at ascend is how do you maintain the
entire notion of
jobs and data and the direct correlation
between the two
for example knowing exactly what code
produced what piece of data and where
as that's the only way to actually
massively automate everything is
to have a really tight binding between
those two
i could see if you had a pipeline it's
got five steps and there's a failure
systems restart it it would be useful to
know be able to look at some state and
say we've done
three of the five steps at least we
don't have to do
those three again but if the fourth step
involved
processing a million records and it
failed
99 of the way through if you have more
fine-grained state
you could then see we only need to do
one percent more and then we'll be done
with step
four is it my understanding of how the
state and the jobs work is that where
you're going
yeah exactly it's the knowing where you
can pick up from
uh it's also knowing whether or not you
can trust the data
so like a classic set of data pipelines
some engineer writes code that says read
this data off of this storage system
process it in this way and then write it
back to that storage system
but the question begs is well what
happens if i change
that code and i and i'm the next
hop i'm hop number two that's processing
data like
is which data is accurate if i fixed a
bug
uh in step one how do i know
if i have to backfill that data or not
and how do i know if it's been
backfilled
or not with that bug fix and no
orchestration tool today
actually can solve that problem for you
which is is it safe to
continue to trust that that data and is
it now
the bug-free set of data this is one of
the things that
is different about data pipelines than
uh let's say software engineering where
i have all my micro services that are
reading on apis
is when i deploy new code and i make
that same
api call but with the fixed code i'll
get the fixed result
in data pipelines because you you
persist data along the way
you have to then if you fix a bug you
have to actually go back and repair
data and that's one of the the biggest
challenges and one of the things we
worked really hard on at ascent to solve
is
the uh binding code to data so that we
know if you're changing code
that that data may no longer be valid
and that awareness that then the system
needs to go prepare that data for you
and that's something that that is really
hard to solve without a really context
aware
a data aware scheduler if you could
solve that
then it would avoid having to delete
all the data and start the entire job
over again when you fix
a bug somewhere in the middle you got it
and that's the
this is the the classic thing that
we as data engineers usually do is the
oh shoot
i found a bug it maybe affects some of
my data but i don't know which one
ah heck just light up a massive cluster
like do it on a friday afternoon when
all of our traffic's low anyways and
just
blast out everything and hope we're done
by monday morning
i am guessing that many of these
individual components
of pipeline are jobs that run on all
kinds of different systems which
have their own interface or query
language how does the
generic automation engine interface
between
itself and specific jobs that run
any possible place yeah ultimately it
has to be smart enough
to understand the code you come at it
from a couple of different directions
things you can actually parse compile
understand
you get a really good semantic
understanding of so
if i'm writing transforms in sql super
easy by comparison
to to really cleanly understand
what's happening with that data to
understand
if that data is partitioned and if
something changes what the impact is
so for languages like that really easy
then as engineers start to actually do
more
complex things in these various uh steps
and transforms of data
really what you do is you you look to
the developer to tell you hints
like so if i'm creating a transform
you're looking for a context of
is this a reduction a partial reduction
a full reduction
a map style operation and when you start
to do that
and you provide convenience layers and
for example
uh a transform and ascend you don't have
to actually ever worry about the e and
the l part
uh every transform a sense tracking the
lineage and maintaining that for you and
passing that as a data frame
and sparked a block of data in and out
of a function that you write
we alleviate that but now because we're
passing data in and out
we can track all the lineage of that
data for you and so
it that's the the sort of piece of trim
down the scope to the common elements
and then give
the developer all the flexibility inside
of that transform function to do
whatever they want but because we can
track the data coming in and out
we can automate the most painful parts
which is the lineage and the profiling
and so on well maybe
i'll ask this in a different way because
what you said was interesting but it
wasn't
what i was trying to understand which is
suppose we have
uh this legacy system and the interface
to it is a script
and we need to invoke that as a step
then
how does that integrate with another
tool is there's
the orchestration engine is our wrappers
or
sidecars or something around it say you
don't know
you're not doing this transform for me
i'm not going to reimplement it inside
of some
other system we're just going to reuse
pieces we already own
can you integrate with those pieces
yeah some obviously not all as you you
migrate
various systems uh but there's there's
definitely ways as you move from uh
these sort of imperative based models
uh and more traditional orchestration
into more declarative systems
to still port over and wrap a lot of
your existing
systems or even plug them in together
so oftentimes you can still have a
traditional orchestration system
dropping off at a dmarc location and
continuing to
to drop there and have uh the the more
modern data pipeline
pick it up from a particular point too
so we see a lot of people
doing a piecemeal ascend has
its own state you've talked about is
that state stored in
some kind of a data store it is yeah we
maintain
a bunch of uh cloud sql rds uh
and then azure database depending on
which cloud
customers in we store all of that
metadata state
inside of a sql database so then you're
relying on the cloud
vendor that they're going to do certain
amount of work to make it
redundant and available yep yeah we lean
really heavily on on each of the cloud
vendors uh
to keep and that we actually run a
pretty consistent infrastructure
uh across each cloud which generally
corresponds to
a lot of blob uh or object stored usage
keats in all
three clouds run dual clusters one for
control plane
one for uh processing and then heavy uh
their cloud sql databases this concept
in the messaging space
at least once delivery meaning i send a
message
i want the system to always fail
on the side of it's going to get there
eventually and if it gets there twice we
can live with that
this sounds like the type of guarantee
you want you want
every piece of data to be processed and
if you process something twice and get
the same answer twice and write it in
the end point
twice that seems like no one would even
notice
is that the right kind of guarantees for
a system like this
yeah it is the especially for like big
data pipelines that are moving around
big blocks of data
you're looking for those sorts of
guarantees
and a couple of others and you're
looking for those
for blocks of data as it moves through
and so the
you're looking for a few things like one
is uh
you're looking for commits of data so
oftentimes you have
data that's uh sitting under a
particular data product right it's a
unified data set and you're updating one
partition of data
uh you need to make sure that you can
commit that partition of data that may
actually be five different files part
files inside of there
and you need the ability to
automatically commit that
and integrity check it and then garbage
collect the old version of that
partition
before you trigger the downstreams right
so you want that ability to
want one deliver it potentially update
it
which you don't necessarily have in
message delivery
in the same way and then know
if it's a partition of data that had a
previous version associated with it
where did that entire partition go and
how do i follow that the previous
calculations and update those
accordingly
i need to do all that uh uh at atomic
stages where each one's committed
so you have stages and you're to rely on
an underlying substrate like a blob
storage to commit chunks of data that
you've processed and you have metadata
that's going to some kind of database
is there any issue of you want
the overall all the stuff you do when
you've completed a step which is going
to include
blob storage and updates to metadata to
be
atomic or can one of those fail and the
other one succeed
generally if one of the steps fails you
generally want to retry
and we put in a bunch of safeguards for
example
everything we write into the object
store is immutable
by design we actually generate random
ids
and every incremental run every attempt
is always written to a different path so
you never have to worry about multiple
attempts or jobs all colliding with each
other and then we use at the metadata
layer
we actually use content addressable
storage to not only point to the right
block but actually even do things like
deduplication
uh if i'm running multiple pipelines
that are actually trying to run the same
code and just generate the same piece of
data
you can do things that deduplicate all
of that this is why we run the micro
batch approach is
you can you run a step if it fails you
can retry it
write it to a different stage commit
that at the metadata layer
and then trigger the downstream system
and make sure that things
continue to rip off one of the areas i
could see
where automation would really help
is if there are steps that you could do
in parallel
you can get the end result faster but
that does create very difficult
programming challenges
which are similar to what you have in
multi-threaded programming where
you're trying to get multiple threads to
all synchronize
at an end point is that something that
ascend or
orchestration engines can help you with
yes they they absolutely do uh the dag
helps here
uh we it's funny we actually have both
our uh header product and our cto
are former chip designers with phds in
electrical engineering
so there's a lot of chip design
influence in how we built our system
and the the general idea is yes anything
you can
parallelize you actually you should
when the the system's data aware and can
bind data to code
you know windows actually converge at
the dag
and so you can run these in parallel
which is super cool
and then you can even do really other
neat optimizations
like specifying priority and inferred
priority from up and down streams
to make sure that the higher priority
stuff gets all the reso
the resources it needs if you maxed out
on the number of resources in this
cluster
so you should do really cool
optimizations
based off of just tiny bits of metadata
that the
the user may provide you could be
talking about a case where we have
six things that are parallelizable
and if we had enough resources we could
do all six in parallel but we don't have
enough resources to do
three so the tool will figure out
orchestration
you can do these three first and then
those three
and as a programmer you don't have to
think about that
exactly you just say as a program you
say i have
these six things that need to happen
they need to converge and this thing
needs to happen after they converge
and here's what's more important than
others
and the the orchestration system is
actually smart enough to do
things like say hey i know i i had auto
scale down to just five nodes but now i
need 30 nodes so let me spin those up
and as soon as those nodes are available
start shoving as much work as i can
towards them
and it can take care of all that for you
automatically and just
it would just track dependencies and
once dependencies of everything is met
it just moves forward that type of
programming it's quite difficult
to do if you try to code it up
that's like the first 10 years of my
career yes that's difficult
all right so let's wrap up the
discussion of the
architecture and orchestration talk
about monitoring first let's talk about
what would you want to monitor about
your pipelines
yeah so when you're monitoring your
pipelines the things that you're really
caring about here is
one if you've implemented data integrity
checks
you really care about if one of those
integrity checks has failed
for example some of our customers have
implemented pipelines that say
if this integrity check fails i want you
to halt everything
and just page me because something
really bad happened
like somebody tried to put in wrong data
ah and so that's one which is purely
data integrity
the second thing that you really want to
monitor for honestly with data pipelines
and this is usually more of an infosec
thing is you want to actually monitor
who's working on those data pipelines
and so there's a lot of this may not be
an unlearning but this is definitely in
monitoring is
you want to know all the changes that
are being made who's making them who's
accessing data
and that's a really important part of of
security
uh so you need to make sure you're doing
that um and we have a bunch of customers
that
essentially have integrated uh into like
sumo logic or splunk
all of the access data that comes out of
the send to make sure that
they have all that then the third thing
that you're looking for as you kind of
go down stack
is you really want to monitor all of the
performance
you want to know how fast are your
pipelines running you want to know
how many resources they take and then
you're actually
for most people if you're not using like
a declarative orchestration system like
ascend
you end up doing a lot of how many nodes
am i running
uh how packed are they uh what's the
utilization of each one of those nodes
where are the the performance
bottlenecks
am i scaling up fast enough am i scaling
down efficiently
and a lot more of an infrastructure
tuning and some of that
you get when you're running on like uh
emr
or cue ball or data bricks but a lot
more of it it comes into the
what are you sending to the jobs uh
there
uh and so that's an infrastructure
efficiency and then the fourth is
actually
in our world of spark efficiency which
is how much data are you reprocessing
unnecessarily so oftentimes it's
are you sending the smallest most
compact most efficient jobs
to your processing an engine at all or
are you doing a lot of inefficient
reprocessing of data
and that you can measure very
quantifiably so those are really the
four things that
uh are valuable to monitor four
categories i should say
we did a episode on distributed tracing
i could see that that either minor might
not be useful
in this pipeline context what's your
take on that
yeah so it's a really good question um
especially across
microservices distributed tracing super
super valuable you know
inside of data pipelines uh it's a
relevant
concept especially as it pertains to the
data itself knowing
where did this piece of data go to and i
think that's one of the ones that
for for most folks is really hard to
know in a classic orchestration
uh if you're not tracking uh you don't
have a system that has an understanding
of the data and the code itself
it's really hard to know where is
everywhere that this
individual piece of data went and that
really
kind of goes back to again having a data
aware system that
knows this piece of data this was run on
by this piece of code and it went to all
these
18 different hops and transform is there
a need for some kind of
audit trailing yes definitely is we
actually uh
we were getting uh at ascend we were
getting a lot of requests for this
for about a year uh and just about a
month ago we even
released a product called ascend govern
basically
because we have such a this data or
system that's super smart about knowing
where everything came from
we really quickly realized that oh
actually we could just pop an api up on
top of all our internal metadata that's
doing all these calculations
and all of a sudden you could actually
say hey for this transform on data
and this column tell me all of the code
that generated the inputs of this and
everything that fed into here
and vice versa this one piece of data
where is everywhere it went to
so part of that govern release was our
entire lineage api
that gives you really good and really
cool insights into
basically just what's happening to all
your data which is fantastic from an
auditability perspective
i could imagine that privacy regulations
might impact this area as well as
how would that work um are you talking
about like uh gdpr or ccp
yeah things like that yep totally this
is one of those ones where
you know when we talked about before hey
if you change your code or you fix the
bug and you have to go and backfill data
and rerun everything same kind of thing
happens when you have to scrub data for
gdpr
if a consumer exercises the right to be
forgotten
you have a lot of their raw data sitting
somewhere in a lake
you have to go find everywhere that that
piece of data has gone and you have to
go get rid of it
and this is in a classic data pipeline
world is really hard
uh if you don't have all the lineage and
the auditing and so on to know
what has to actually get those you know
it's not just inserts or
additions that get uh propagated but
deletes have to actually get propagated
too
and one final question you mentioned
some of the tools in this space like
airflow and
beam and i can see for some sets of
problems you
could accomplish this with hadoop or
with some of the
abstraction layers on top of hadoop that
are
more declarative like pig or hive
where if you have your own
infrastructure then you can
just run these tools on your own
infrastructure versus
more like a hosted solution and pipeline
automation as
a service where do you see things going
and
do you think this will be uh just
another
feature that all the cloud vendors if
they don't already have it
will offer it as one of their product
lines obviously i'm really bullish
uh and uh optimistic on the the need for
more advanced
scheduling and orchestration you know
technologies like uh
pig and hive uh for example i i've used
hive a bunch in the past
these all you know technologies sit on
top of that processing engine and they
they provide a great query or hive does
uh provides a great query interface that
goes compiles down into hadoop jobs
and the basically what you get out of
this is is kind of like what you get
with spark sql
uh that runs on spark which is a
queryable interface that has a query
planner and a query optimizer
the the missing link is still on top of
that is you ran a query at one point
that generated some data
when you think about the data
orchestration for data pipelines that
are continuously running
what you really actually need is like
this continuously running
query planner and query optimizers that
is perpetual that is constantly running
to distracting everything that's moving
all the data through
uh as opposed to just for one query and
snapshot in time
and so i think that's like that is where
the next big frontier is because that's
where we're spending all of our time
right now and so i do really believe
that when we look at things like
infrastructure management container
management
data pipelines is one of these next
domains where
we can move things towards more
declarative models that have these
domain specific
service or scheduling and orchestration
layers that really can
optimize and so to the latter part of
your question
wholeheartedly believe yes we're going
to see all of the cloud vendors
continue to try and invest and expand
here because
it's the thing that gives data
engineering teams so much leverage and
freedom to build more faster
sean where can listeners find your
company
uh to find our company uh we are at
ascend
dot i o a s c e n d dot io
where can listeners find you i am
on twitter and linkedin and very rarely
on a few other platforms but i would
stick with twitter and linkedin
under uh my name uh just at sean s-e-a-n
nap k-n-a-p-p great put that in the show
notes
as well great sean thank you so much for
speaking
to software engineering radio thanks so
much for having me robert this is a ton
of fun
this has been robert blumen thank you
for listening
thanks for listening to sc radio an
educational program brought to you by
ieee software magazine
for more about the podcast including
other episodes visit our website
at se radio.net to provide feedback you
can comment on each episode on the
website or reach us on linkedin
facebook twitter or through our slack
channel at scradio.slack.com
you can also email us at team
sc-radio.net
this and all other episodes of sc radio
is licensed under creative commons
license 2.5
thanks for listening